this is dr. Charles Parker and you're
listening to core brain journal it's a
place where I connect both fresh
discoveries and interesting different
perspectives from advanced mind science
with the realities of real people and
everyday life down on Main Street well
welcome folks here we are one more time
dr. Charles Parker this is core brain
journal and I'm gonna have to tell you
folks you just have to get ready I mean
if you're driving a car and you have
your seatbelt fastened that's a good
thing because if you're just around the
house or you're at the gym I suggest you
prepare to sit down and gather your
thoughts because we have a guest that is
going to burn your ears off and light up
your brain in all kinds of constructive
ways so welcome Daniel this is Daniel
smacking burger from Encinas California
welcome Daniel thanks for having me
really appreciate you coming on board
I'm going to introduce him and then
we're gonna hear a lot more about who he
is and how he's thinking about the
evolution of mind science so Daniel
smacking burger is the consummate
polymath with a background in systems
science and human behavior and is the
founder of the emergence project he's
the anchor of the scientific team as
well as provides the vision behind neuro
hacking movement at neural hacker.com
now some of you out there are saying ok
guys what is this whole neuro hacker
thing I'm gonna pass that one over you
Daniel and tell us a little bit about
yourself and how you got into the whole
neuro hacking movement please so neuro
hacking pretty much means applied
neuroscience how can we work with
various technologies and modalities to
increase various aspects of mind brain
function cognitive and psychological and
widely it is technology agnostic meaning
whether we're talking about biochemical
technologies or whether we're talking
about
neuro tech kinds of technologies like
transcranial stimulation transcranial
ultrasound transcranial magnetic deep
stem tDCS TSEs any of those kinds of
technologies or whether we're talking
about brain training via neurofeedback
or any other kind of brain training or
whether we're talking about genomic
solutions in terms of either modulating
gene expression or CRISPR technologies
or psychotherapeutic or any kind of
personal development technologies
anything that is affecting the mind
brain system and the associated
physiology environment systems that can
optimize human experience and human
capability we're interested in well
Daniel I'm glad that you summarized it
so succinctly but you just covered the
entire field of mind science in about
two sentences I think it's amazing that
you were able to do that but I like the
idea of technology agnostic because
you're saying let's be inclusive let's
not get all of our ducks in one row
let's think about these in a from a
complexity point of view and you and I
had an opportunity to speak about this
earlier and I think that whole thing of
complexity systems if you could talk a
little bit about that and how pulling
these disparate ideas together might be
constructive yeah when the field of
psycho no pharmacology started complex
system science was not well developed
wasn't really developed at all and so
our best scientific methodology was
still variable isolation reductionism so
we're looking specifically to try and
understand what dopamine does or what a
particular molecule that affects some
part of you the dopamine system a
presynaptic dopamine agonist or a
dopamine receptor modulator you know
some some particular part of it what
that does but that means we're trying to
understand one part in isolation of the
rest of the whole and to be able to do
clinical trials on that appropriately
we're kind of averaging everything else
together and then we see do we get some
kind of statistical lift beyond placebo
and if we do then that seems interesting
even though that bell curve
has people getting significantly
different experiences on opposite ends
the bell curve
they're obviously attributable to other
things right the way that one variables
interfacing with the rest of the system
and so complex system science allows us
to look at a lot more variables a lot
more complexly and look at their
interactions and their synergies synergy
defined as the behavior of whole systems
that is unpredicted by the havior of the
parts taken separately in isolation and
so one of the problems when we were
trying to isolate variables is the
synergies between variables get missed
and this is why and the way we've
practiced medicine where we have
gastroenterology neurology oncology etc
all the diseases that start in one
system and move to another system right
issues that start in the gut caused
mucosal barrier dysfunction and end up
causing neurologic issues because
they're between systems we end up
missing so much of the pathology of the
pathology and what we find is also in
radically complex systems everything to
various degrees in effects everything
else so we need to study that the the
causal interactions much more complexly
we also get causal recursion where one
thing can affect another variable but
then that variable can in turn come back
and reflect that variable both either in
a regulatory capacity or with positive
feedback loops and so obviously when we
look at the success of psychiatric
medicine for all kinds of psych diseases
currently compared to what a system that
was truly adequate for addressing them
would be we have a huge Delta and the
fields of Integrative Psychiatry North
Molecular Psychiatry you know
interdisciplinary approaches to mind
brain science have started to look at a
lot more variables right rather than
just give a in chain neuro chemical
modulator in the form of a med look at
why did that chemical get off balance in
the first place and really was it just
that one chemical is it a whole set of
things they got out of balance and did
it originate in an inflammatory
condition and a gut condition in a
psychological condition and head trauma
right
and then we also start to see that not
only are there a lot of variables that
are involved but they're different sets
of variables for different people and
this is where we start to get towards
personalized medicine and then
personalized psychology psychiatry and
personalized development so say we're
looking at anxiety or autism or
Alzheimer's and we're looking at all the
things that we know causally are
associated right or at least all the
things where we have a some kind of
correlation and so we'll find maybe
heavy metals are actually statistically
meaningfully correlated with this
particular kind of neurodegenerative
disease but so are other forms of Organa
toxin of organic toxins right
organophosphates VOCs maybe microbial
imbalances in the mucosal system may be
parasitic infections may be subclinical
humoral infections may be methylation
disorders may be certain kinds of
psychological disorders you see all of
these things are correlated but not one
for one which means they statistically
correlate there probably have a causal
influence sometimes but not all the time
because that represents one pathway of
deviation from homeostasis that can lead
to pathophysiology that can lead to some
set of symptomology occurring and when
we talk about anxiety or Alzheimer's or
any kind of disease what we're talking
about is some similar kinds of symptoms
from some similar kinds of tissues but
the underlying pathologist can be quite
different that's why we haven't
succeeded in really being able to
address them and so you need to develop
an underlying causal landscape a causal
ontology of all the things that could be
associated it could be causal how to do
differential diagnosis across all of
those and then how to be able to
understand different therapies in terms
of the underlying mechanisms that are
involved and then what is the weighted
subset of that whole causal landscape
that's going on for this person and then
what what therapies what synergy of
therapies and in what order of
operations are going to be ideal for
them and this is where we move towards
real personalized medicine personalized
psychotherapy and then be
on the baseline of wellness personalized
enhancement and development that gets to
synthesize the best of everything that
we know today you know while you're
talking you say it's so exceedingly well
pardon me for being effusive with you a
little bit but it's just so interesting
to hear you talk because it's what so
many of us struggle with every day it
doesn't matter whether you're a purely
traditional psyche or whether you're a
patient coming into a psychosis
everybody's looking for the complexity
really in their mind they're thinking
complexity but they don't have a vehicle
a road a path to consider and wrap their
arms around complexity and then there's
no thing where the complexity is not
only the variables that you're speaking
about but it's the complexity of time as
time comes into the whole situation
because so much of function is time
related and so much of what we're
dealing with is not time related it's
fine that label to be that way to the
next hundred years yeah we also have
when we're at a time we have all of the
conditions that have very delayed
causation delayed onset and this is
something that always makes diagnosis
tricky as if something has a rapid onset
following a pretty clear cause it's a
little bit easier to treat but if
something has a either a rapid onset but
not following any clear cause or maybe
the clear cause that it followed was
simply a last trigger of a whole causal
chain that moved it in the symptomology
then it's very easy to miss attribute it
and so we need to be able to do
diagnosis thinking about things that
might have happened a long time ago but
not resulted in symptomology and then as
we as we're treating of course here's
one of the things I would say is very
deep to our goals is we have this
internal regulatory system right this
endogenous regulatory system and it's
not one regulatory system but you can
think of all the different regulatory
axes as a comprehensive regulatory or
cybernetic system and we're regulating
pH and redox interactions and glucose
and you know transmitters and you know
all the things
within specific ranges so if someone's
dopamine is really low and I just give
them a in chain dopamine that agonist
without asking why was it low was it low
because they aren't eating enough
protein that contains the amino acid
precursors is it because they can't
digest the protein because of a issue in
their stomach they can't absorb it
because if an issue in their intestines
can they not convert those amino acids
can they not convert the tyrosine into
l-dopa into dopamine are there enzyme
deficiencies are there so if I go
straight to giving the in chain agonist
and of course whatever else was affected
downstream I'm not going to be
supporting right and say it was say it
was a tyrosine mechanism well that's
also affecting their thyroid right it's
also affecting so many other systems and
I'm gonna get some side effects because
now I'm creating a fixed level of that
chemical independent of the body's
realtime regulation of it which is gonna
throw out the balance with the you know
literally trillions of other chemicals
that it should be interacting with with
more complexity than that and I'm
creating exogenous dependence right so
rather than the body being able to
self-regulate it's depending on external
regulation and so now there's ongoing
dependence our goal is that any good
system of medicine and good system of
psychiatry and good system of biohacking
neuro hacking should be supporting the
endogenous regulatory systems to have
increased regulatory capacity and we can
really define health as the robustness
and resilience of the regulatory
capacity of the entire system and then
we can think about aging actually as
decreased homeostatic resilience on some
of the axes and then we can think about
disease as some deviations from
homeostasis that exceed the homeostatic
capacity of one or more of the axes that
lead to pathophysiology so then our goal
really becomes in preventing illness in
life extension and in fundamental
optimization of the human experience and
condition
how do we increase the resilience the
robustness and the antifragility
of the entire set of regulatory systems
and a good intervention should seek to
do that right it should seek to support
endogenous upregulation rather than
override it well you know one of the
things that as you're talking I'm sure
the complexity of your thinking is so
fascinating but I said something there
are just at the very close that I wanted
to jump on because what you're really
saying in a way and correct me if I'm
wrong is that we're really dealing when
you're dealing with the complexity you
have a complexity of answers you don't
have a single answer so one of the
things that happens is people come a guy
like me and they say you know I've got
this problem well how come I have to do
all these supplements and these
medicines and all these other things
because there are so many things can't
you just give me one thing and you know
I'm a very primitive level of this
understanding compared to where you are
but I think that's an interesting issue
to address with our our audience because
that's a frequent problem for our
audience how do we actually deal with
the complexity on a street level right I
would say the Silver Bullet mentality is
a broken mentality in every area every
area that we apply it whether we're
hoping that the answer to getting our
finances together is a lottery ticket or
the answer to getting buff or
psychologically well or anything it's it
always requires any kind of development
of any system requires continuous varied
kinds of input and entropy is always
acting on systems and so there is a
minimum and it's acting on on all
systems right you have oxidative stress
on cells you have excitotoxin stress you
have mutation that's occurring you've
got and so it's you've got entropy
occurring on all these systems you need
to be putting in at least as much energy
and by energy here I don't mean glucose
and Jaime putting in at least as much of
the appropriate kind of input as is
eroding and to just even keep up right
and just like anyone knows that if
someone works out for ten years
gets buff this can be the moment they
stop working out they start losing it
and it is entropies this just kind of
universal recycling process of that
which is not no longer useful right and
so then it starts moving those parts to
be used for something else so any kind
of health any kind of resilience
requires continuous input and the
appropriate kinds of continuous input so
we know that there are so many different
minerals depending upon which list you
read of how many are essential at 72 or
84 or 92 right but there's so many
minerals that are essential for health
there's so many vitamins so many
phytonutrients so many macronutrients
and even a deficiency of one of them can
lead to a debilitating disease right
just D being low leading the rickets or
C being well leading to scurvy or b1
leading a berry berry and so Liam if we
want to not see it's not just them being
low enough that they go into acute
pathology it's also the sub clinical
pathology of systems that are working
they're just not working optimally and
now we're not just talking about
nutrients and but we're also talking
about input that supports detox an input
that supports antioxidant
anti-inflammatory
is not a nutrient per se but it is part
of what's going to support system
regulation so yes I would say that
anyone who wants to be really healthy
and vital and optimized has to take full
responsibility for what that means and
not expect that there's a very easy
doctor solution or a single kind of
solution and just embrace that as the
the physics of universe I mean that is
so
solutely true I mean that is what we
deal with either we're gonna deal with
the complexity now and and some of us
may be interested in how do we package
the complexity yeah do have to
understand the complexity they can't
just go out and shotgun the complexity
because that absolutely won't work it
has to honor the integrity of the system
in some constructive way and even though
there there is a complexity involved
that the integrity of that system has to
have somehow be packaged in a way that
the person on the street can actually
you know what's what's a what's a good
systems approach to that particular
problem right when I think what you're
doing with the podcast here is offering
people education so that they can feel
more empowered in what are likely
appropriate avenues for them to dive
deeper into what we're seeking to do
over at no hacker collective is you know
we're we're developing specific
technologies so they can go direct to
consumer right now we're developing more
that might not go direct to consumer but
be you know mediated by some kind of
therapists but what we're really looking
to do long range is a platform that
allows us to integrate all the kinds of
complexity personalize them to an
individual and their goals and actually
make the interface very simple for them
and so if we can collect all of people's
biometrics from their genetics to their
clinical chemistry to their quantified
self sleep tracker motion track or
whatever we can take all those biometric
data pieces and we can take psycho
metrics we can do cognitive assessments
that look at various aspects of
cognitive function and psychographic
assessments psychoanalytic assessments
then and then not just look at each of
those metrics in relationship to their
own reference range but look at each of
them in relationship to each other how
did this particular picture arise
in terms of factoring all of the
underlying inter causal dynamics then we
can start to get a real picture of
what's going on for someone and you know
this person's sleep disorder different
than this person's sleep disorder right
this person's anxiety different than
this person's in terms of underlying
mechanics in terms of the you know
genetics and fundamental space of that
person and then be able to synthesize
what are all of the technologies that do
have known efficacy for sleep and then
relate them to underlying mechanics or
anxiety or whatever it is and then be
able to say these ones are going to be
most effective for this person at this
time you know highest probability so
this is N equals one optimization the
clinical trial can't do that right it
can only say there is some left with a
bell curve compared to placebo even
though the people in one in the bell
curve and the other having totally
different experiences when you try to
put everybody on the front of a bell
curve now we're not saying okay I have
this device or supplements or meditation
technology or whatever I'm gonna give it
to ruin because I have a hammer I'm
gonna say that everything is a nail
right and we can say you have anxiety so
take a benzo are you having xiety so do
this breathing technique or meditation
technique and it might help some but if
the person's anxiety is related to a
parasitic brain access disorder none of
those solutions are gonna fix it and if
it's related to a head trauma and
there's some actual neural circuitry to
address none of those are going to fix
it but that doesn't mean there aren't
things that could fix it and it doesn't
mean that they wouldn't show up
differently if we know how to do the
right assessments and then be able to
direct people to you know what is the
highest probability of greatest success
for them which is actually now not that
complicated but it draws on all the
complexity of everything we know both
about psychology physiology the mind
brain interface and all of the
diagnostic and therapeutic modalities so
it has a simultaneous activity of ruling
out and ruling in so it's not just yep
ruling out Frank its ruling in
and and that's a very very interesting
point because that takes us over to the
affirmative prospect so how does this
thing actually work effectively as
opposed to here's what the problem is
here's how we can see this pathology
okay this is this is a sick broken
system you're saying well that's really
only above the picture and if we get
lost over there which I think in truth
many of us are then we're arrested we're
developmentally arrested we have a lot
of great insight rate in the world of
integrative medicine and functional
medicine I think have been doing a good
job progressively of trying to see how
do we factor more systems so we're gonna
look at the gastro neurology and the
neurology and the oncology and the
rheumatology together right and then
we're gonna look at the various
intercostal worlds together the genomics
and the microbiome X and the
transcriptomics and the proteomics and
the you know that that way of looking at
the body and we're gonna look at the
different kinds of deviations from
homeostasis toxins nutrient deficiencies
genetic disorders infections right and
how do we work with those and try and
make some sense out of this and so you
can see various people who are kind of
at the cutting edge in those spaces
doing a better job of synthesizing more
things now synthesizing and aggregating
are different right aggregating is the
shotgun approach which just says all
right well all these have some
effectiveness let's kind of try all of
them synthesis is well these ones are
effective for for these kinds of
mechanisms not just these kinds of
engine conditions they can have lots of
mechanisms leading into them so how do
we do the differential diagnosis and
know what to do then for that person and
how do we do right order of operations
right so if it's functional medicine
gets into quite a lot when you need to
treat a gut barrier disorder before
trying to address blood toxicity issues
otherwise you're gonna can or
Rheumatology because you're going to
keep having inflammation from from tight
Junction issues whatever so I think
they're doing a very good job but
they're doing it like you go to a con
and you look at all the cutting-edge
research that's happening in various
fields it's more than any human can
actually synthesize and when you look at
all the medical journals that are coming
out with actually good underlying
mechanistic insights it's again more
than any human can synthesize which is
why it takes this kind of AI platform
methodology to be able to vet and
synthesize at scale and then make all of
human knowledge available to individual
practitioners and individual people so I
was like a Wikipedia of the mind some
constructive way yeah yes
AI is artificial intelligence yes just
to say that because I know some of our
listeners may wonder what a is so then
the next question after that is do you
you are developing a system then you're
developing ways of doing this and you're
codifying and how you know is this gonna
happen in a computer model of some kind
is it going to be it sounds like you're
going in that direction that when you
feed the material in and you do a
certain and number of tests then you can
feed it in and pop something out that's
going to be more easily accessible than
then just plain thinking it through yeah
definitely so you can see that we
already have labs that automate some of
the suggestions based on kind of
standard protocols from what they see in
the lab so you get the lab back and you
have depending upon say you're doing
that you know gut barrier assessment
then based on what's showing up in the
lab you'll see some generated pages of
common best practices you also already
have systems of electronic medical
records that start putting some pieces
of the data together start giving you
some analytics so that's the trend in
that direction those are just relatively
low intelligence systems and
so what what is interesting is as we can
start harvesting a lot more biometric
data then it becomes less and less
understandable by an individual person
in real-time so if we start doing whole
genome sequences and want to look at the
whole genome right that's a lot and then
it's not just looking at individuals
snips right individual genes and their
polymorphisms it's looking at the
combinatorics on that and now that
scales very quickly and then that still
doesn't tell you about gene expression
and so then we're looking at clinical
chemistry and metabolomics
transcriptomics etc and so but all we
can understand the underlying mechanisms
that are happening and we can build
systems to be able to model this better
and do a better job of making more sense
of more different kinds of data in a
synthesized fashion so that's the goal I
mean how can you say all that in one
breath
I mean it's so interesting you know so
then how are you actually breaking that
down in neuro hacker I mean I don't want
to ask for any proprietary but just to a
little bit of an idea because it sounds
so very large to the questions you're
raising or so enormous in terms of
practical how does one do that to make
it yeah well if you go to you know
hacker comm right now you won't see
anything about anything we're talking
about you will see a little bit of
information on complexity science
applied to neuroscience and you will see
some cognitive enhancement supplements
for sale so we're a relatively new
organization and so we're starting
somewhere like every organization needs
to and for us well we knew the goal was
C I'm talking about diagnostic methods
here but let's look at the therapeutic
side for a moment and you've got the
disease model side which is you know how
do we get people back to wellness from
some diagnosed disease
then you have the enhancement side and
so neuro hacker has started in terms of
its forward facing offerings on the
direct-to-consumer enhancement side and
if you think of neural hacking kind of
as a subset of biohacking that is
specifically focused and and that just
means applied technologies for personal
enhancement but we're specifically
focused on the mind brain space so
enhancing cognitive and enhancing
emotional and psychological both
well-being and capability there's a lot
of different technologies that are
effective as we were mentioning you know
so we were looking at whether we wanted
to develop better systems of EEG
neurofeedback or better systems of
transcranial lasers for up regulating
neuronal ATP or better systems of
computer-based psychotherapy or that can
you know work on a widely through a
platform or the better kind better kinds
of neural chemical solutions and they're
all very meaningful and they're
differently meaningful for different
kinds of people and so our goal is to
synthesize to be able to have a space
where if someone had a goal no matter
what the goal was in the psychoneurosis
and no matter what the underlying
physiology they had going on there could
be a best synthesized resource for them
and so we started in the know tropic
space of cognitive enhancement because
we'd work in that space deeply and we
knew that we could do very potent of
life enhancing things for people they
were not currently available on the
market and we could do that easier then
we could build this AI system and so
this was a and then you know from there
a whole line of direct-to-consumer
biochemistry so specific kinds of
nutraceuticals that we didn't see on the
market anywhere else because we're
working with this complex systems
framework of not trying to say alright
we're we have a sleep mode and we're
working with gaba or melatonin or you
know but
what are all the things that are
involved and how do we up regulate the
endogenous circuitry and obviously to do
this at full scale we need to be able to
do it in a customized fashion and that's
what requires this underlying system so
we're starting with not customized but
center of the bell curve very effective
for most people and that's what we
currently have then we're moving into
phenotype specific so before it's fully
personalized we find that there are
handfuls of kind of neurochemical
phenotypes so like in the Walsh work
you've looked at under an over meth
later is a different underlying
structure right under an over
catecholamine urge ik under an over
cholinergic CNS stimulation so we can
get more effective just through those
kind of categories and then move into
full customization but it's also of all
the things one could do how likely is a
vagal nerve stimulator versus a
transcranial stimulator versus this
breathing technique versus these
biochemical gaba
Eric's going to be most useful for them
even at that level so we started
building technologies in each of these
categories some are in market already
some are still in R&D and over the next
year a lot will be going coming to
market and this allows us to be able to
grow our research team and you know
continuing development and the
underlying platform we're working on but
you know that that has some years before
its meaning meaning ly applicable well
the issue is because you're just going
to have you're really in kind of a data
acquisition mode from what you're saying
you're you you know generally what the
problem is but then you're codifying and
breaking it down and doing some serious
data acquisition because then you can
push the button and have some configure
so yeah we are as far as that
acquisition goes not mostly in terms of
feedback from current things we're doing
that's useful this is why
we do trials but it is doing doing
structured reviews of all of the fields
to know where the current state of the
art is of the entire field if you
synthesize all the knowledge which is
something that is not for whatever
reason commonly done or well done and
then being able to see what should our
hypothesis generation within a
particular space be once we already have
looked at everything that is known in
that space and what we can abstract from
all those partial insights together and
as you know if you're doing that in
connectomics if you're doing that in you
know neurogenesis if you're doing that
in genomics it's there's a lot of you
know takes work yeah yeah that's it's
deep it's gonna it's gonna cost I mean
to do that to actually pull the
laboratory data together it's going to
be if you have some interested people
and some well-trained people and people
who are thinking along the same path who
have the same delightfully curiosity
objectives that you have it could happen
I mean it's just the question of putting
putting kind of a forgive the grandiose
expression kind of a new world order of
how do we how do we codify Dada how do
we pull it together yeah and the poet's
the others the key part because machine
learning assessing big data is already
there and there's a number of systems
doing that but when the interactions are
as complex as these ones are even
tremendous amounts of computation don't
give us all the insights just via
computational brute force you have to
actually develop models you have to
develop underlying ontology of how this
complex human regulatory system works
and then be able to utilize those models
as ways of interpreting the data and
that's one of the things that we're kind
of uniquely focused on
sounds so interesting so when you go
over to the website you have some I've
seen them you have some great videos
that break down some of this I mean it's
been a while since I was over there
you're looking like maybe you're trying
to think of which video was but it
seemed to me there was a video that I
saw is like oh my gosh this I had a very
interesting interesting moment and I am
I miss remembering that I think we have
some videos on the site currently I
don't know that we have any speaking
about the future of say Diagnostics or
interpretation like this but we do have
ones that are discussing why a system
science approach is needed and then some
of how we came up with this particular
cognitive enhancement chemistry from a
systems theoretic perspective and
because it's not only useful for
interpreting diagnostic that it's also
useful building technologies that work
across multiple mechanisms
simultaneously and one understand the
synergy of those mechanisms so when
we're talking about enhancing people's
cognitive capability are we talking
about modifying acetylcholine or
glutamate or dopamine or other
catecholamines or ion channels or
changing the phospholipid membranes or
we're probably talking about all of
those things right and so and then with
acetylcholine are we talking about
changing how it gets across the synapse
are we talking about changing how it is
up taken and the postsynaptic receptor
or we and so what we did in that space
because there are so many people who are
not using adderall via prescription but
off-label adderall and other kind of
what you call smart drugs for their
midterms their finals their tech start
up where it really does have meaningful
side effects and and even you know Red
Bull and multiple doses of 300
milligrams of caffeine with it's
important to get that both something
like adderall
something like the energy drinks will
enhance a certain element of
productivity and focus while decreasing
statistically known to decrease other
key elements of cognitive capability
plus producing dependence plus producing
side effects and so we wanted to see can
we support people in their desire to be
more clear and productive and capable in
the presence of ever increasing
attention distractions in ways that are
more effective and not harmful and so
that that required is looking at well
when people are really seeking cognitive
enhancement what are they looking for
and they're not just looking for focus
they're looking for a combination of
focus and short-term memory and
long-term memory and speed of memory and
specific memory and digit span and
verbal fluency and emotional things that
come along with it like emotional
resilience and connection to drive and
so we kind of from a cognitive science
point of view modeled what is everything
that people look for there and then we
looked at what is everything known about
the underlying physiologic pathway is
known to correlate with each of those
subjective States and cognitive
capabilities then as character affects
all of those pathways and then start our
design process from there so that's you
know a systems theoretic perspective
works both on may slide design science
and they interpreting Diagnostics in
both of those worlds so the question
then is a guy who practices again this
is gonna be sort of a proprietary
question but I'm curious because I use
testing and I wonder how a person like
you or your team decides which group
you're going to use for the tests that
you're going to acquire so that it could
have a more diffused body of position so
that so that a number of people can use
it effectively how do you actually do
what the laboratory is going to be or
which laboratories to use how does that
happen
yeah so as far as laboratory testing
goes I have to make my FDA disclaimer
statement right now we're talking about
the future of medicine psychiatry just
abstractly but as far as neuro hacker
goes we don't have anything to say about
medicine or psychiatry because we can't
say anything about that and we aren't
prescribing labs and etc so we just tell
people to go to a doctor and get those
done but as far as research in that
space coast how do we determine how
would I determine what I think is a good
laboratory test or not well there's a
few things first we have to look at
sensitivity and specificity
how many false negatives how many false
positives do we have from that lab by
comparing it to other known best of
assessments over an appropriate database
so that's kind of pretty standard and
then we have to look at the turnaround
time for getting the data back we have
to look at the cost of it and all other
aspects of viability and then we have to
look at how relevant the data that it's
showing us is and and what the
interpretive confidence margin around
clinical applications from that data
looks like and so you know if we're
doing parasitology and we really were
just interested in do we see the
parasite right but if we're doing some
immunology connected to parasitology and
we're running CD 57 to say that someone
has Lyme's disease but we know that it's
not actually specific to Lyme it could
be all kinds of infections then a CD 57
for me means some kind of humoral
infection usually and that's about all
it means right so I can use it as a
indicator along with many other
indicators for a complex set of
assessments but I have to be careful
about my how I interpret that particular
metric now as far as the platform that
we're interested in we want to make a
platform that can upload any tests
right so whether someone's comprehensive
stool lab is coming from doctors data or
Genova or whatever right
if the sensitivity and specificity is
known to be high enough to the
meaningful confidence margin we want to
be able to upload any of them and be
able to run data interpretation across
them in the future but it's also
important to know that I'm very
passionate about developing diagnostic
technologies further because when when
we want to do complex complex disease
case solutions in particular I I want to
look at all of the inflammatory markers
although to me and all the rheumatologic
markers right I want to look at all of
the kind of nutrient markers I look at
all the genetics that I can see oh and
look at all the clinical chemistry
because it ends up being that even some
of the more obscure things show up and
that you wouldn't have thought to be
associated show up in many of the
difficult cases and non-obvious ways and
so to even say order of operations of
which diagnosis to do first which to
later I'd rather get them all cheaper
all more reliable and be able to just do
a lot more data on everybody and so
there are kinds of technology that could
make that possible like being able to do
metabolomics on mass spectrometry could
make metabolomic assessment very cheap
and in the near future
right across 2,500 metabolites be able
to continuously run those and things
like you know single drop of blood on a
technology like gene radar is getting
very interesting and the next step
beyond that is I think laser
interferometry where we can test a
number of elements in the blood just
through scattering patterns diffraction
patterns on laser light going in you
could imagine if that technology got
very far that we could testing all of
the biometrics nearly continuously
running big data on those and you can
imagine how much we could learn and so
that those are things that we see in the
future of medicine that's an amazing
picture because what you're talking
about is
measuring you know the things that
you're measuring are phenomenal because
you're actually talking about all kinds
of different pieces of the body so to
speak you know anything from excrement
to urine to mouth swabs to you know a
lot of there's a lot of biomedical
variables in that whole situation that
you were talking about many of which I
don't know about myself because I'm just
a commonplace a practitioner I while I'm
listening to you I'm amazed because I'm
thinking of my own self discovery
process while I'm listening to you and
how I was going along thinking hey this
really worked but then it did so then I
went into another level and say oh this
works but hey here's another place with
this new thing that I learned but it
doesn't work so it's been one long
process for me on a on a personal level
of finding these different things that
is why I value speaking to a person like
yourself who has this this depth of
knowledge with these like that whole
thing is they spectral with the blood
cell what was that what was that called
you had some you're shootin laser into
with laser and laser interferometry is
there's very little that I can access
right now and we're not sure how much
we'll be able to assess but I I have a
hope that the answer will be a lot and
so the deal there is you're actually
just putting a beam of light coherent
light into say your wrist vein and then
it bounces back but based on what's in
the blood what molecules are in the
blood the frequencies of light will
scatter and they'll scatter differently
based on different molecules and
different densities of them so you can
tell blood glucose without taking the
drop of blood right but then the
question is which molecules in the blood
could we assess and could it be a lot
more of them and could it be mostly all
of them and so whether it's mass spec on
urine doing you know metabolites or
whether it's lilies or interferometry or
who knows
biofield assessments I think I think we
what we know for sure is we will be able
to get more and more data more often
more Rubik with ously so that we can
understand patterns across lots of
people but even within a single person
and as that happens it progressively
exceeds the ability of individual people
to understand fully without some aid in
processing and that's where as the
diagnostic technologies get better the
interpretive technologies need to get
better and that's what the
interpretative models that the doctors
and people can learn but also processing
those the data through those models so
to translate a little bit if you take
some of these labs like Jen over Great
Plains or whatever you and you find some
level of confluence of successful
information from them that would just be
a piece of what you're envisioning
because they would only cover the
dimension that that lab is skilled at
great right and so you have to have a
number of different you have to have a
not one module that you have to have
several different modules it's just
going to be worked up and you have to
figure out integrate and synthesize
those modules into into one I have one I
shouldn't say one answer but one series
of answers right so I'm not a I'm not a
doctor I'm a researcher but I've worked
with a number of Integrative doctors on
difficult
traditionally incurable cases and where
so we looked at what are all the things
that the literature knows is initially
correlated and then how do we assess for
those and that would look like I would
have a relationship with one lab to test
Michael plasmas and another one to test
viruses and another one to test
parasitology and protozoa and another
one for the best Rheumatology and other
ones for scans and that was actually
usually several different types for
different kinds of brain scans and other
ones for me coastal barrier function
right and other ones for
mold and biotoxin information other ones
for environmental toxins and so what
that means is that's just so burdensome
on the clinician and on the office staff
have to set up all those relationships
send them different places and spin the
blood this way and etc that we really
need the field of Diagnostics to get
fundamentally better otherwise some
diseases are incurable that aren't
really incurable simply because what it
takes to figure them out is too hard
that is so true we see that every day I
mean the the whole spectrum of how you
actually just get the test taking it
requires you know forget managed care
and answering it to myriads of people in
managed care who with high school
education look that is how do you just
fill out the paperwork and get that get
the laboratory information back to to
pull it together and then how do you
spend the time to put it together and
get a and and put together a program for
a person yeah it's great it's definitely
difficult right now why are you why
you're talking I was thinking about an
experience I had with some really
interesting neurofeedback people when I
add the office up in DC encephalography
when you were talking about that
particular technique because even now
and people out there need to know that
you could put a band on and shoot red
infrared spectrums near-infrared hemo
encephalopathy you can shoot it right
through the skull have it bounce out and
get readings on what's going on with the
oxygenation and the prefrontal cortex
yeah and that's there that's here right
now which is and it's not difficult to
do I mean the technology is pretty
doggone simple to do require I should
say it's true well yeah I mean the earth
near technology is pretty simple easy
technology and EEG is becoming simple
enough that home EEG units are actually
meaning meaningful data sources and home
HRV units are good and so this is one
what's the HRV
heart rate variability okay and so we
which is a major indicator of autonomic
nervous system and so there it this
whole field what we call quantified self
the various kinds of devices that allow
self measurements I think is going to be
a huge part of the future of medicine
where people take more and more
responsibility for their own well-being
and this means that already people have
the ability to buy their own supplements
and you know do a number of their own
therapeutic modalities but they also
they need to be able to track right if
it if they really want to understand
what's going on and so I think both of
those are increasing over time because
they're gonna be able to do that
assessment and then that'll be somehow
hooked back to your database of hey it's
working or no it's not and right what do
we do next
so this is in the Dreaming phase for us
in terms of all the things that that
platform will be able to do but we do
hope that it gets to the place where we
can do the kinds of complex data
processing we're talking about and
included then is if there is data
missing that we would need to be able to
figure it out that we can actually
recommend what kind of Diagnostics
people get we could recommend doctors
for them to go work within a network but
we could also be able to recommend which
of the home assessment technologies are
best from vetting them so that you know
we're empowering people to have more
ability to participate in their own
well-being now that's a reason for all
of our listeners to go right over to
neuro hacker and get hooked up
immediately because they need to be on
your list right now because if you then
have next week or next month or next
year some way of beginning this process
of measurement that you folks have
signed off on that you think is going to
be valid and useful then they need to be
there I mean our whole audience this
ours is a small audience I mean there's
a bigger audience out there that's
curious about this
I think anybody that ever listens to
this should be just immediately hooked
up with neuro hacker I'm quite
enthusiastic about having had the chance
to speak with you because what you're
talking about is where we're I think so
many people want to be but don't know
how to get there myself included I think
you know you know it's it's such an
interesting place to be and to even
envision the possibilities are there
because the mind is seem you know
completely out there it's just we can't
even talk about it it's just over our
heads nothing to talk about all these
different things
IgG is still complex if as mundane is
that simple test is a lot of people it's
a belief system to some you know it's
still it's this Galileo moment you know
the Sun is rotating around Rome I know
it is I can see it is so we don't need
to worry about that and that that is
what's going on
so we really do have to close Daniel I
really I know you're a little bit under
the weather and I can't tell you how
much I appreciate you taking the time to
join or join us here and and be with our
audience I mean this is going to be one
of our most outstanding interviews
because why because people are going to
have to listen to it more than once
because you are so deep and so
interesting that people are going to are
going to share this and really be
interested to learn more from you so
thank you very much I appreciate it
dr. Parker at so much respect for what
you're doing and it was a real honor to
be here thanks for listening to core
brain journal we're working every day
behind the scenes to bring you reports
that connect research benches with those
Street trenches here we share the
complexity of mind science because as
you know details really do matter one of
the most pervasive misunderstood
challenges is how commonplace
medications like those written for ADHD
are used so regularly without clear
guidelines if you think you'd like more
specifics take a minute to download my
two-page PDF
with video links and references on the
absolute essentials of how to start ADHD
medications they're easily available at
core brain journal comm forward slash
start thanks for listening do connect
and stay tuned together we can make a
difference
[Music]